<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of, by the reuerende father in God, Richarde by Gods prouidence Bishop of Elye for the churchwardens and inquirers of euery seuerall parishe vvithin his diocesse, in his visitation, holden in the yeare of our Lord God, 1573.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Ely. Bishop (1559-1581 : Cox)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1573</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10194.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23025668</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23025668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of, by the reuerende father in God, Richarde by Gods prouidence Bishop of Elye for the churchwardens and inquirers of euery seuerall parishe vvithin his diocesse, in his visitation, holden in the yeare of our Lord God, 1573.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Ely. Bishop (1559-1581 : Cox)</author>
                  <author>Cox, Richard, 1500-1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Bynneman, for Humfrey Toy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1573]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26100:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <p>¶ ARTICLES to be inquired of, by the reuerende Father in God, Richarde by Gods prouidence <hi>Biſhop of Elye, <hi>For the Churchwardens and Inquirers</hi>
               </hi> of euery ſeuerall Pariſhe vvithin his <hi>Dioceſſe, in his viſitation, holden</hi> in the yeare of our Lord GOD, 1573.</p>
            <p>PRINTED AT LONDON, by Henry Bynneman, for Humfrey Toy.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26100:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26100:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>¶ To the Perſons, Vicars, and Curates, Churchwardens, and Inquirers, vvithin the Dioceſſe of Ely.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as in my former Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I deliuered out certayne Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as well vnto you of the Clergie, as vnto the Churchwardens, and other ſworne men, to be diligently obſerued and kept: it ſhall not be néedefull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate and inioyne the ſame agayne. In caſe any newe matter of diſorder maye appéere vnto you, by the inquirie of my Articles, ye ſhall doe well and duetifully to receiue and take the true ſenſe, and meaning of the ſayd Articles, to be in place and ſteade of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, bothe vnto the Clergie, and alſo to the Laytie, as we vſe to call them. Which Articles, by the way of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I thought good to myniſter vnto you, to the intent both that ye may by the helpe of them more eaſily fynd out, and declare all the diſorders whiche are vſed in your Paryſhes, to the euill example of others, and to the highe diſhonor of Almightie God. And that alſo by your faithfull information vpon your othes, I may be the better able to redreſſe all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and faultes, to the edifying of the people in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſh, and to the glorie of the Almightie and euerlaſting God. Theſe Articles yée Churchwardens muſte diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and truely anſwere to euery Article according to your othes:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26100:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
IN primis whether your Perſon or Vicar, doe preach againſt the vſurped power of the Biſhop of Rome, and his romiſh doctrine and errors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Quenes Maieſties Iniunctions.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Item whether he reade twice in the yeare, the confeſſion concerning the principall articles of Religion ſet forth by the Archbyſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, and other Byſhops.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Item whether you haue one Sermon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quarter at the leaſt, in your pariſhe Church.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Item whether there be any Monuments of ſuperſtition remayning, as Images, Croſſes, holy water ſtockes, Roodeloftes, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Item whether there be any in your pariſhe that ſpeaketh agaynſte any pointe of Religion, nowe eſtablyſhed in this Realme, or any that be deſpiſers, mockers, or gaineſayers of Preachers and Miniſters doing their duties.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Item whether there bee any knowne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or any receyuers of ſuch as doe not conſent to the Queene hir Maieſties Supremacie.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Item whether your Chancell, Church, and Churchyarde be in good and ſufficient reparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Item whether your Perſon or Vicar haue moe benefices than one, &amp; whether your Curate ſerue moe cures than one.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Item whether your Curate reade diſtinctly, ſo that he may be heard and vnderſtanded of the pariſhioners, &amp; whether he hath ſpeciall Licence vnder the Ordinaries Seale.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Item whether your Curate reade an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely,
<pb facs="tcp:26100:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->when there is no Sermon.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Item whether the Churchwardens do col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and take, of thoſe that do not come to church vpon the Sundayes and Holidayes, the forfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of twelue pens, to the vſe of the poore, for euery time that they be ſo abſent without iuſte cauſe.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Item whether a Certificat be made at the leaſt euery quarter, of all ſwearers, blaſphemers of Gods holy name, Drunkardes, Adulterers, inceſtuous perſons, Fornicators, Rybaudes, Baudes, or receiuers of ſuch inconuenient people and of ſtrange women with chylde, whoſe huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes are vnknowne, or any perſons that are vehemently ſuſpected of ſuch faults, &amp; al ſowers of diſcorde betweene neyghboures within your paryſhe.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Item whether the Statute of the prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the poore be duely obſerued and kept: if not, in whome the faulte is, and whether any refuſe to contribute to the reliefe of the poore.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Item whether there be any that doe ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornely contemne, or deſpiſe the order of Admy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the holy Sacramentes, ſette forth in the Engliſh tongue, or haue not receiued, or do obſtinately refuſe to receyue the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at the leaſt three times in the yeare.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Item whether there bee any cloth hanged on the wall, where the high alter ſtoode, and the table often commaundements fixed to the ſame.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> Item whether your Perſon, Vicar or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
<pb facs="tcp:26100:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->ſay or ſing his ſeruice, in ſuch decent veſture as is preſcribed by publique authoritie.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Item whether any of your Pariſhe after that he be excommunicated, doe at any tyme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to the Churche, at Diuine ſeruice, not beeing abſolued and reſtored to the Church agayne, and whether any of your Pariſhe keepe any ſuche excommunicated perſon companie.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Item whether the Children bee inſtructed in the Engliſh Cathechiſme, laſtly ſette forth by authoritie, euery Sundaye and Holydaye, before Euening praier, by the ſpace of one whole houre, and if they bee not, whether the faulte bee in the Parentes and Maiſters of the Chyldren, or in the Curate neglecting his duetie.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether ther be admitted to the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Communion, any notorious ſinners within your pariſh, without open reconciliation &amp; declaration of repentance for the ſame offence.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> Item whether the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions bee read quarterly, by the Perſon, Vicar or Curate.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Item whether any of your Paryſhiones walke, talke, or otherwiſe vnreuerently bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues in the Churche, or vſe any gaming abroade, or in any houſe, or ſitte in the ſtreates, or Churchyardes, or any Tauerne or Alehouſe vppon the Sundayes or Holydayes, in tyme of Common prayer, ſeruice, Preaching, or reading of the Homelies: or whether any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Alewiues, Victualers, or Typlers
<pb facs="tcp:26100:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->do ſuffer them.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> Item whether any Butchers, Bruers, Shomakers, or others, vſe to bring, carie, or ſell any ſuch things vpon Sundayes or Holydays, in the time of Common prayer, Sermon or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Homelies, and whether any other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer dothe vtter any wares or Marchandize in the like times.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23</hi> Item whether the Churchwardens, doe ſee the names of all Preachers that preache in their paryſh Churches, to be noted in a boke for that purpoſe, &amp; whether euery Preacher do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his name, &amp; of whom he had his Licence.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24</hi> Item whether any man trouble or moleſte the Churchwardens for doing their dueties.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether the Churchwardens be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the Perſon, Vicar, or Curat, without whoſe conſent they may not be choſen.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26</hi> Item whether the Churchwardens haue prouided theſe bookes following, that is to ſaye, the Engliſh Bible in a great volume, the boke of ſeruice, the bokes of Homelies, with the Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt rebellion, bokes of Pſalmes, the boke of holy Articles, with Canons and rules of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in Engliſhe, the booke of the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions, the booke of aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the table of degrees of Matrimonie, the ten Commaundementes, and the Byſhops In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, the bookes of peculiar prayer ſet forth at any tyme, at the coſtes and charges of the Pariſhioners.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <pb facs="tcp:26100:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
               <hi>27</hi> Item whether the Paraphraſes of Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, or elſe the expoſition of Maſter Muſculus vpon the Goſpell of Saint Mathewe, be hadde and prouided, at the charges of the Pariſhe and Parſon, or Proprietarie, equally borne betwene them.</p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether the Quire be cumly &amp; orderly kept<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether they haue a fayre &amp; cumly Table, of two yeardes and a halfe (if the Quire wyll ſerue) for the Communion, with a faire linnen cloth to lay vpon the ſame, and ſome couering of Silke, Buckram, or ſuch lyke, for the cleane kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereof.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29</hi> Item whether there bee any within your Pariſhe that dothe adminiſter vpon the goodes of any deceaſed, without authoritie from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie, whereby the Infantes and Creditors, commonly be defrauded of their dueties.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <hi>30</hi> Item whether the Perſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, doth vſe any other ſeruice, than by publique authoritie is ſette forth, or alter or chaunge the ſeruice of the booke of Common prayer, or any parte thereof otherwiſe than it is ſette forthe.</p>
            <p n="31">
               <hi>31</hi> Item whether the Perſon or Vicar hath made a terrey of their glebe Landes, Paſtures, Medowes, Cloſes, or Gardens, belonging vnto their benefice, by the chiefe of their Pariſhe, and whether they haue preſented the ſayde terrey, accordingly vnto their Ordiuarie.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>32</hi> Item whether the Parſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, hath yerely before the .xx. day after Eaſter,
<pb facs="tcp:26100:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->exhibited to the Biſhop, or his officers, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſurnames of ſuche perſons in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, beeing .xiiij. yeares of age, and vpwarde, whiche receyue not the holie Communion. And ſuch alſo as refuſe to be examined by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Church, in the Cathechiſme.</p>
            <p n="33">
               <hi>33</hi> Item, whether any be admitted by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vicar, or Curate, to be godfathers, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers, vnleſſe they haue receiued the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or can ſay the Cathechiſme.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <hi>34</hi> Item whether you knowe any perſon by preaching, or in worde by talke, maynteyning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctrine againſt the worde of God, or againſt the godly articles, or againſt the booke of ſeruice confirmed by full authoritie of the Churche of England, and of the whole Realme.</p>
            <p n="35">
               <hi>35</hi> Item whether any thing which hath bene complayned of, is not yet redreſſed.</p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>36</hi> Item whether any in your Paryſhe do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue or diſprayſe the boke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer, in any part (ſet forth by authritie of Parliament) or ſpeake againſt the Homelies, or do mayntaine or holde any erronious opinions, contrarie to the worde of God, and the Lawes of the Realme.</p>
            <p n="37">
               <hi>37</hi> Item whether there hath beene any fraye made in your Churches, or Churchyards, to the diſturbance of Gods ſeruice, or to the euill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the reſt of the Paryſhe, and if there hath ben, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal preſent by whom it was made, when, and after what ſort.</p>
            <p n="38">
               <hi>38</hi> Item whether there be any Scholemaſter
<pb facs="tcp:26100:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->within your paryſhe that doth teach any Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſchole, either priuately, or openly, whether they be licenced ſo to teach, howe long they haue taught, and what their names bee.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>39</hi> Item whether there bee any Legacies withholden, giuen to the Churche or poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or mending of high wayes, or otherwiſe by the Teſtators. In whoſe handes it is, by whom it is giuen, and by whome it is withholden.</p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>40</hi> Item whether your Churchwardens doe truely Adminiſter the goodes of the Church, and in the preſence of the Miniſter, make a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their office yerely, and at the end of their accounte delyuer vp the money, and chooſe newe Churchwardens once euery yeare.</p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>41</hi> Item whether any man haue put awaye his wife, or any wife abſente hirſelfe from hir huſbande without iuſt cauſe or without authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from their Ordinarie, or any that hath mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within the degrees prohibited by the Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and other Lawes within this Realme, ſet forth in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <hi>42</hi> Item whether there be any conuenient &amp; ſtrong Cheſt, for the poore mans Boxe.</p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>43</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether your Perſon or Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, do miniſter the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion to any forei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or ſtraunger, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of any other Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, without the ſpecial Licence of the Byſhop, or his officers, or the miniſter of that place from whence the ſaid Foreiner or ſtranger doth come.</p>
            <p n="44">
               <hi>44</hi> Item whether euery Moneth your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb facs="tcp:26100:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->Vicar, or Curate, doe reade openly in the Churcht, the Proclamation ſet out of late by the Queenes Maieſtie, for the calling in of ſeditious Bookes, as <hi>Hardings, Saunders,</hi> and ſuch like, to bee deliuered to the Ordinarie, according to the tenor and meaning of the ſayde Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which Proclamation is to bee hadde at the coſtes and charges of the paryſhe.</p>
            <p n="45">
               <hi>45</hi> Item whether they do exerciſe themſelues in godly ſtudie of holy Scriptures, and in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous bringing vp of youthe, as in teaching of them their Cathechiſme, and other Godly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes from time to time.</p>
            <p n="46">
               <hi>46</hi> Item whether decently, and orderly they goe in their apparell, according to the Booke of Aduertiſements, lately ſet forth in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="47">
               <hi>47</hi> Item whether they be reſident vpon their Benefices, and maintayne Hoſpitalitie to their habilitie. And whether their Perſonage houſes, and Vicarage houſes with other the edifices, and houſes of eaſements thervnto belonging &amp; appertayning, be in good and ſufficient reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and if they be not reſident, whether they let their Benefices to ferme to their Curates accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute.</p>
            <p n="48">
               <hi>48</hi> Item whether they vſe to praye for the Queene hir Maieſtie in their Churches, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte the people to obedience of hir grace, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Magiſtrates being in authoritie vnder hir.</p>
            <p n="49">
               <hi>49</hi> Item whether your Perſons, Vicars, or Curates be maried or no, and if they be not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26100:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->they kepe in their houſes any ſuſpected wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, vnder the name and coloure of their But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, kinſwomen, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="50">
               <hi>50</hi> Item whether they obſerue and keepe the order for the bringing of the Corſe to the buriall, according to the Booke.</p>
            <p n="51">
               <hi>51</hi> Item whether they doe viſite the ſicke and impotent perſons, to comfort them in the time of their ſickneſſe with neceſſarie doctrine out of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, neceſſarie for that purpoſe, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them alſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the poore, and other charitable deedes.</p>
            <p n="52">
               <hi>52</hi> Item whether your Perſon or Vicar bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght his benefice, or elſe came to the ſame, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned it by fraude, guile, Simonie, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlawful meanes.</p>
            <p n="53">
               <hi>53</hi> Item whether your Perſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, doe expounde the Scriptures, as the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Epiſtle and Goſpell, after they haue read them in the Churche, or Homelies in reading of them, without eſpeciall Licence.</p>
            <p n="54">
               <hi>54</hi> Item whether the boke, or Regiſter wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Daye, Moneth, and Yeare, of euery wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Chriſtening, and Burying is, or ought to bee written and noted, bee well and diligently kept.</p>
            <p n="55">
               <hi>55</hi> Item whether you haue at the common charge of the Paryſhioners, a cumly and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Pulpit, ſette and placed in a fit place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Church, and the ſame cleanly and ſemely kept for the preaching of Gods worde.</p>
            <p n="56">
               <pb facs="tcp:26100:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
               <hi>56</hi> Item whether your Perſon, Vicar or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, were made Prieſtes in the Reigne of King Henrie the eyght, or Queene Marie. And if hee were, then whether he hath read openly in your Paryſhe Churche, the Articles of Religion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordying too the Statute in that behalfe lately made.</p>
            <p n="57">
               <hi>57</hi> Item to inquire of what value the Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage is, if there be any Vicarage in your Pariſh, and who is the Patron and giuer thereof. And if there bee a Curate, what wages hee hath, and who doth pay it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
